<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
   <teiHeader>
      <fileDesc>
         <titleStmt>
            <title>A godly exhortation whereby Englande may knowe: What sinfull abhomination there nowe dooth flowe.</title>
            <author>Pecke, Edward.</author>
         </titleStmt>
         <editionStmt>
            <edition>
               <date>1588</date>
            </edition>
         </editionStmt>
         <extent>Approx. 7 KB of XML-encoded text transcribed from 5 1-bit group-IV TIFF page images.</extent>
         <publicationStmt>
            <publisher>Text Creation Partnership,</publisher>
            <pubPlace>Ann Arbor, MI ; Oxford (UK) :</pubPlace>
            <date when="2011-12">2011-12 (EEBO-TCP Phase 2).</date>
            <idno type="DLPS">A09212</idno>
            <idno type="STC">STC 19521</idno>
            <idno type="STC">ESTC S110387</idno>
            <idno type="EEBO-CITATION">99845941</idno>
            <idno type="PROQUEST">99845941</idno>
            <idno type="VID">10874</idno>
            <availability>
               <p>To the extent possible under law, the Text Creation Partnership has waived all copyright and related or neighboring rights to this keyboarded and encoded edition of the work described above, according to the terms of the CC0 1.0 Public Domain Dedication (http://creativecommons.org/publicdomain/zero/1.0/). This waiver does not extend to any page images or other supplementary files associated with this work, which may be protected by copyright or other license restrictions. Please go to https://www.textcreationpartnership.org/ for more information about the project.</p>
            </availability>
         </publicationStmt>
         <seriesStmt>
            <title>Early English books online.</title>
         </seriesStmt>
         <notesStmt>
            <note>(EEBO-TCP ; phase 2, no. A09212)</note>
            <note>Transcribed from: (Early English Books Online ; image set 10874)</note>
            <note>Images scanned from microfilm: (Early English books, 1475-1640 ; 1667:10)</note>
         </notesStmt>
         <sourceDesc>
            <biblFull>
               <titleStmt>
                  <title>A godly exhortation whereby Englande may knowe: What sinfull abhomination there nowe dooth flowe.</title>
                  <author>Pecke, Edward.</author>
               </titleStmt>
               <extent>[8] p.   </extent>
               <publicationStmt>
                  <publisher>Printed by Edward Allde, and are to be solde by Hugh Astley at Saint Magnus Corner,</publisher>
                  <pubPlace>At London :</pubPlace>
                  <date>1588.</date>
               </publicationStmt>
               <notesStmt>
                  <note>By Edward Pecke.</note>
                  <note>Title and imprint within decorative border.</note>
                  <note>Incomplete; consists of 8 pages only (ends with A5).</note>
                  <note>Reproduction of the original in the British Library.</note>
               </notesStmt>
            </biblFull>
         </sourceDesc>
      </fileDesc>
      <encodingDesc>
         <projectDesc>
            <p>Created by converting TCP files to TEI P5 using tcp2tei.xsl,
      TEI @ Oxford.
      </p>
         </projectDesc>
         <editorialDecl>
            <p>EEBO-TCP is a partnership between the Universities of Michigan and Oxford and the publisher ProQuest to create accurately transcribed and encoded texts based on the image sets published by ProQuest via their Early English Books Online (EEBO) database (http://eebo.chadwyck.com). The general aim of EEBO-TCP is to encode one copy (usually the first edition) of every monographic English-language title published between 1473 and 1700 available in EEBO.</p>
            <p>EEBO-TCP aimed to produce large quantities of textual data within the usual project restraints of time and funding, and therefore chose to create diplomatic transcriptions (as opposed to critical editions) with light-touch, mainly structural encoding based on the Text Encoding Initiative (http://www.tei-c.org).</p>
            <p>The EEBO-TCP project was divided into two phases. The 25,368 texts created during Phase 1 of the project (2000-2009), initially available only to institutions that contributed to their creation, were released into the public domain on 1 January 2015. The approximately 40,000 texts produced during Phase 2 (2009- ), of which 34,963 had been released as of 2020, originally similarly restricted, were similarly freed from all restrictions on 1 August 2020. As of that date anyone is free to take and use these texts for any purpose (modify them, annotate them, distribute them, etc.). But we do respectfully request that due credit and attribution be given to their original source.</p>
            <p>Users should be aware of the process of creating the TCP texts, and therefore of any assumptions that can be made about the data.</p>
            <p>Text selection was based on the New Cambridge Bibliography of English Literature (NCBEL). If an author (or for an anonymous work, the title) appears in NCBEL, then their works are eligible for inclusion. Selection was intended to range over a wide variety of subject areas, to reflect the true nature of the print record of the period. In general, first editions of a works in English were prioritized, although there are a number of works in other languages, notably Latin and Welsh, included and sometimes a second or later edition of a work was chosen if there was a compelling reason to do so.</p>
            <p>Image sets were sent to external keying companies for transcription and basic encoding. Quality assurance was then carried out by editorial teams in Oxford and Michigan. 5% (or 5 pages, whichever is the greater) of each text was proofread for accuracy and those which did not meet QA standards were returned to the keyers to be redone. After proofreading, the encoding was enhanced and/or corrected and characters marked as illegible were corrected where possible up to a limit of 100 instances per text. Any remaining illegibles were encoded as &lt;gap&gt;s. Understanding these processes should make clear that, while the overall quality of TCP data is very good, some errors will remain and some readable characters will be marked as illegible. Users should bear in mind that in all likelihood such instances will never have been looked at by a TCP editor.</p>
            <p>The texts were encoded and linked to page images in accordance with level 4 of the TEI in Libraries guidelines.</p>
            <p>Copies of the texts have been issued variously as SGML (TCP schema; ASCII text with mnemonic sdata character entities); displayable XML (TCP schema; characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or text strings within braces); or lossless XML (TEI P5, characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or TEI g elements).</p>
            <p>Keying and markup guidelines are available at the <ref target="http://www.textcreationpartnership.org/docs/.">Text Creation Partnership web site</ref>.</p>
         </editorialDecl>
         <listPrefixDef>
            <prefixDef ident="tcp"
                       matchPattern="([0-9\-]+):([0-9IVX]+)"
                       replacementPattern="http://eebo.chadwyck.com/downloadtiff?vid=$1&amp;page=$2"/>
            <prefixDef ident="char"
                       matchPattern="(.+)"
                       replacementPattern="https://raw.githubusercontent.com/textcreationpartnership/Texts/master/tcpchars.xml#$1"/>
         </listPrefixDef>
      </encodingDesc>
      <profileDesc>
         <langUsage>
            <language ident="eng">eng</language>
         </langUsage>
      </profileDesc>
      <revisionDesc>
         <change>
            <date>2010-09</date>
            <label>TCP</label>Assigned for keying and markup</change>
         <change>
            <date>2010-09</date>
            <label>Apex CoVantage</label>Keyed and coded from ProQuest page images</change>
         <change>
            <date>2010-11</date>
            <label>Mona Logarbo</label>Sampled and proofread</change>
         <change>
            <date>2010-11</date>
            <label>Mona Logarbo</label>Text and markup reviewed and edited</change>
         <change>
            <date>2011-06</date>
            <label>pfs</label>Batch review (QC) and XML conversion</change>
      </revisionDesc>
   </teiHeader>
   <text xml:lang="eng">
      <front>
         <div type="title_page">
            <pb facs="tcp:10874:1" rendition="simple:additions"/>
            <p>¶ <hi>A Godly Ex<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>hortation, whereby Englande maye knowe: What ſinfull abhomination, there nowe dooth flowe.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>AT LONDON Printed by Ed<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ward Allde, and are to be ſolde at Saint Magnus Corner by Hugh Aſtley.</p>
            <p>Anno. 1588.</p>
            <pb facs="tcp:10874:2"/>
         </div>
         <div type="poem" subtype="to_the__reader">
            <pb facs="tcp:10874:2"/>
            <head>To the Chriſtian <hi>Reader.</hi>
            </head>
            <lg>
               <l>I Touch not thoſe which godly be,</l>
               <l>my pen blames none of them:</l>
               <l>I wiſhe no ill to he or ſhe,</l>
               <l>but good vnto all men.</l>
            </lg>
            <lg>
               <l>But this I wiſhe with all my hart,</l>
               <l>God graunt it maye be ſo:</l>
               <l>That wicked perſons may conuert,</l>
               <l>and all their vice forgoe.</l>
            </lg>
            <lg>
               <l>I wiſhe that vertue may increace,</l>
               <l>in euery Chriſtians hart:</l>
               <l>I wiſhe that wicked vice may ceaſe,</l>
               <l>and quite be laide a parte.</l>
            </lg>
            <lg>
               <l>I wiſhe that <hi>England</hi> may ſo frame,</l>
               <l>it ſelfe vnto Gods woord:</l>
               <l>That other nations ſeeing the ſame,</l>
               <l>may praiſe the liuing Lord.</l>
            </lg>
            <lg>
               <l>The cauſe why that I made this book,</l>
               <l>is this I tell you plaine:</l>
               <l>I would all thoſe that heerin looke,</l>
               <l>from vices ſhould refraine.</l>
            </lg>
            <lg>
               <pb facs="tcp:10874:3"/>
               <l>And not all thoſe alone I ſaye,</l>
               <l>but all the reſt beſide:</l>
               <l>God graunt vs now and alway,</l>
               <l>in him for to abide.</l>
            </lg>
            <lg>
               <l>Accept this Treatiſe in good parte,</l>
               <l>moſt humbly I deſire:</l>
               <l>And let me haue of euery hart,</l>
               <l>good will euen for my hire.</l>
            </lg>
            <lg>
               <l>Although it rude and ſimple be,</l>
               <l>yet doo it not deteſt:</l>
               <l>But where as any faultes you ſee,</l>
               <l>of them make you the beſt.</l>
            </lg>
            <lg>
               <l>That I by hearing good reporte,</l>
               <l>of this the firſt of mine:</l>
               <l>May be encouraged with comforte.</l>
               <l>to write an other time.</l>
            </lg>
            <lg>
               <l>I truſt at this my ſimple woorke,</l>
               <l>ther's none will be offended:</l>
               <l>Except be thoſe that meanes to lurke,</l>
               <l>in ſinne while life be ended.</l>
            </lg>
            <closer>
               <signed>Edward Pecke.</signed>
            </closer>
            <trailer>FINIS.</trailer>
         </div>
      </front>
      <body>
         <div type="poem">
            <pb facs="tcp:10874:3"/>
            <lg>
               <l>Haſt thou forſaken Couetouſneſſe,</l>
               <l>that gréedy gulping ſinne?</l>
               <l>Haſt thou giuen ouer thy great exceſſe,</l>
               <l>which thou dooſt wallow in.</l>
            </lg>
            <lg>
               <l>Or haſt thou now exiled quite,</l>
               <l>the vice of Fornication?</l>
               <l>With enuious hate and deadly ſpite,</l>
               <l>and all abhomination.</l>
            </lg>
            <lg>
               <l>From ſwearing, lying, and all deceites,</l>
               <l>dooſt thou thy ſelfe refraine?</l>
               <l>All polling meaſures, and crafty waightes,</l>
               <l>with hart dooſt thou diſdaine?</l>
            </lg>
            <lg>
               <l>If that thou haſt forſaken thoſe,</l>
               <l>with all the reſt beſide:</l>
               <l>Then maiſt thou ſay as I ſuppoſe,</l>
               <l>thou haſt no more but Pride.</l>
            </lg>
            <lg>
               <l>I doubt thy ſelfe thou canſt not cléere,</l>
               <l>of neuer a one of them:</l>
               <l>The which I haue rehearſed héere,</l>
               <l>with this my ſcribling pen.</l>
            </lg>
            <lg>
               <l>Wherfore it makes me to lament,</l>
               <l>that ſuch vices ſhould dwell:</l>
               <l>In thée, for whome Chriſte ſhed his blood,</l>
               <l>as witneſſeth his Goſpell.</l>
            </lg>
            <lg>
               <pb facs="tcp:10874:4"/>
               <l>He that dooth walke thy Coaſtes abroad,</l>
               <l>O <hi>England</hi> at this time:</l>
               <l>May ſée what ſtrife and great diſcorde,</l>
               <l>is in the Children of thine.</l>
            </lg>
            <lg>
               <l>Where one there is O <hi>England</hi> now,</l>
               <l>that walkes aright in thée:</l>
               <l>There is a thouſand I dare abowe,</l>
               <l>that followes iniquitie.</l>
            </lg>
            <lg>
               <l>O <hi>England,</hi> is it not a ſhame,</l>
               <l>and a filthy ſhame to thée:</l>
               <l>That thou which haſt a Chriſtians name,</l>
               <l>ſhouldſt make this true to be?</l>
            </lg>
            <lg>
               <l>The mighty God of his méere grace,</l>
               <l>did ſend his woord to thée:</l>
               <l>To that intent thou ſhouldſt imbrace,</l>
               <l>the ſame moſt louingly.</l>
            </lg>
            <lg>
               <l>But thou forſookeſt his woord and grace,</l>
               <l>when he gaue it to thée:</l>
               <l>And willingly thou didſt imbrace,</l>
               <l>all kinde of vanitie.</l>
            </lg>
            <lg>
               <l>And now thou art ſo train'd therin,</l>
               <l>thou wilt it not forſake:</l>
               <l>But daye and night in horrible ſinne,</l>
               <l>thy pleaſure thou dooſt take.</l>
            </lg>
            <lg>
               <pb facs="tcp:10874:4"/>
               <l>What eyes be they that can refraine,</l>
               <l>from ſtreming flouds of teares:</l>
               <l>To ſée the vices that doo raigne.</l>
               <l>in theſe thy latter yéeres?</l>
            </lg>
            <lg>
               <l>Wherfore, O <hi>England</hi> now repent,</l>
               <l>thy wicked life amend:</l>
               <l>That God, thy God, incontinent,</l>
               <l>his grace to thée may ſend.</l>
            </lg>
            <lg>
               <l>And if thou haue any reſpect,</l>
               <l>vnto thy health at all:</l>
               <l>His righteous lawes doo not neglect,</l>
               <l>but come when he dooth call.</l>
            </lg>
            <lg>
               <l>And with an hart and right good will,</l>
               <l>his woord ſée thou obaye,</l>
               <l>And then he will defend thée ſtill,</l>
               <l>from Sathans filthy way.</l>
            </lg>
            <lg>
               <l>Thy Vſurers if thou root out,</l>
               <l>and hoyſers vp of rentes:</l>
               <l>With all the Rogiſh ruflling rout,</l>
               <l>which dooth defile thy tentes.</l>
            </lg>
            <lg>
               <l>Then maiſt thou beare Chriſtes name aright,</l>
               <l>then maiſt thou boldely ſay:</l>
               <l>Thou art a Chriſtian cléere and bright,</l>
               <l>
                  <gap reason="illegible" extent="1 line">
                     <desc>〈1 line〉</desc>
                  </gap>
               </l>
            </lg>
            <lg>
               <pb facs="tcp:10874:5" rendition="simple:additions"/>
               <l>But of this thing thy ſelfe aſſure,</l>
               <l>O <hi>England</hi> now I ſaye:</l>
               <l>So long as ſuch in thée endure,</l>
               <l>from God thou goeſt aſtray.</l>
            </lg>
            <lg>
               <l>Therfore with Chriſtes Goſpell true,</l>
               <l>thy Vſurers reproue:</l>
               <l>With all the reſt of Sathans crue,</l>
               <l>which he ſo well dooth loue.</l>
            </lg>
            <lg>
               <l>And ſo if that they will repent,</l>
               <l>by Preaching of Gods woord:</l>
               <l>If the<gap reason="illegible" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> will not Incontinent,</l>
               <l>on them place Iuſtice ſwoord.</l>
            </lg>
            <lg>
               <l>This thing if thou doo put in vre,</l>
               <l>thy wicked vice ſhall ceaſe:</l>
               <l>And faithfull loue with vertues pure,</l>
               <l>in thée ſhall ſtill increaſe.</l>
            </lg>
            <lg>
               <l>ſwoord of Iuſtice be not ſlack,</l>
               <l>
                  <gap reason="illegible" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>léep not in ſilence ſo:</l>
               <l>Leaſt little <hi>England</hi> goe to wrack,</l>
               <l>through vice which there dooth ſlewe.</l>
            </lg>
            <lg>
               <l>Awake therfore, take vp thy ſwoord,</l>
               <l>and view <hi>England</hi> about:</l>
               <l>And root out thoſe, which at Gods word.</l>
               <l>
                  <gap reason="illegible" extent="1 line">
                     <desc>〈1 line〉</desc>
                  </gap>
               </l>
            </lg>
            <pb facs="tcp:10874:5"/>
         </div>
      </body>
   </text>
</TEI>
